My Daughter Is under Too Much Pressure
over the University Entrance Exam
I am the same age as you,
but I have a daughter
who is in her final year of high school.
She has six cousins
from both sides of the family.
All of them have graduated
prestigious universities.
Yes.
She feels a lot of pressure over this.
She thinks that I'd feel ashamed
if she fails to go to a top university,
given I had her late
and raised her dearly.
Every day she is pained
under great pressure.
I can't study on behalf of her.
So I'd like to know
if there's a way to relieve her pain
and give her comfort through prayer.
Is that such a sad thing?
(Audience Laughter)
But my daughter is having a hard time.
You can tell her, "You don't necessarily
need to go to a good school.
Don't worry. I'm thankful
as long as you are healthy."
Even so, she still feels the pressure.
Just keep telling her that.
I wanted to seek advice on
whether there'd be a way of prayer
that can grant her wisdom and courage.
Maybe a prayer for University Entrance.
You're basically saying you want a prayer
that will get her into a good school.
Aren't you?
If you say so.
(Audience Laughter)
Try having a baby at 42.
You can't not have high hopes.
(Audience Laughter)
Wouldn't anyone have high hopes?
You are the reason she is stressed out.
You have high expectations for her.
She won't feel pressured
if you let go of your expectations.
But she's smart.
She knows even if I don't show it.
So please give me advice on
what prayers will bring her wisdom.
Pray this way: "My daughter doesn't
necessarily have to go to university."
"But other kids have to."
"So please, Buddha,
help other kids get in first."
"If there's a spot left,
let my daughter in."
You will see great results
by praying this way.
(Questioner) Okay.
Try memorizing. Can you do that?
(Questioner) "Please let all the other kids
get good spots at good universities."
(Questioner) "If there's ever a spot left,
please accept my daughter then."
(Sunim) Yes
(Applause)
Yes. If you do so,
how would the Buddha see you?
Would he not think
you are worthy of praise?
If you pray: "Buddha,
my daughter isn't that smart,
but please grant her admission
to a good school."
"Please grant her a spot
by replacing a smarter student."
How would the Buddha think of you?
Would he not think you are impudent?
He would think so.
Blessings will never come your way.
So pray as I have told you,
and tell your daughter this:
"You don't have to go to
an elite university."
"Just go wherever you're qualified to go.
I'll support you regardless."
She may say, "But don't you still have
high expectations for me?"
You can say, "It's true that I had
high hopes till now."
It would be a lie to say you didn't.
So tell her, "It's true, but listening to Sunim's lecture today,"
"I was told he dropped out
of high school."
"Even so, he is living a fulfilling life."
"I thought about it and realized
that school isn't all that matters."
"So don't pay too much attention
to your cousins, live your own life."
"Don't follow other people's lives."
"We're living in a new era
where each person should live"
"their life their own way."
Tell her that. Do you understand?
Yes.